Boiler 1 was a D-type water-tube boiler produced
by English Boiler in 1953.
It was installed and started making steam
for the campus in 1965.
It was then upgraded to a new larger unit
in 2005.
Water-tube boilers are designed to circulate
hot combustion gases or flue gas around the
outside of a large number of water-filled
tubes.
As the flue gas passes through the tubes,
it heats the tubes, which then heat the water
to produce steam.
The tubes extend between an upper header,
called a steam drum, and a lower header, called
a mud drum or sometimes, a water drum.
Tubes are either straight or bent into simple
or complex shapes.
Water-tube boilers are designed to circulate
hot combustion gases or flue gas around the
outside of a large number of water-filled
tubes.
As the flue gas passes through the tubes,
it heats the tubes, which then heats the water.
As more heat is transferred, the water temperature
keeps rising until it reaches the saturation
temperature and water changes phase from liquid
to vapor or steam.
Boiler 1 can produce 25,000 pounds of saturated
steam per hour at the pressure of 100 psi,
at a temperature of 338 degrees Fahrenheit.
The steam is sent out to the buildings on
campus through an underground piping system.