The heating plant at U.W. Stout was
built in 1965. It was designed to
supply the entire campus with steam
for heating, hot water, and cooking.
We have a closed-loop system. Steam
is generated at the heating plant
and sent in underground pipes to the buildings.
After use, the steam is condensed into water
and pumped back to the plant
where it can be used again.
The original plant had 3 boilers.
Two burned coal and natural gas. The other boiler
was converted to burn natural gas and fuel oil.
In 1972 the plant was expanded,
and a fourth boiler was added.
The boiler burned natural gas as well as fuel oil.
All four boilers are water tube boilers.
This means the water is inside the tubes,
and this is where it is converted to steam.
In 2005 the oldest boiler was
replaced with a newer, larger one.
The new boiler is more efficient and built
with its own stack making it more versatile.
Originally, the plant had pneumatic controls.
In 2000 the plant was converted to electronic
controls, and in 2021 the controls were converted
to Program Logic Controllers, or PLC’s. These
are more accurate, efficient, and user-friendly.
There have been many upgrades to the plant.
All boiler feed pumps, condensate pumps,
and forced draft fans now are equipped
with Variable Frequency Drives, or VFD’s.
We have also one turbine-driven boiler feed pump.
In 2020 and 21 we added a 42,000-gallon fuel oil
tank to ensure a reliable fuel supply and
removed all boiler coal-burning equipment.
All four boilers are now capable of
burning fuel oil and natural gas.
The plant is operated and staffed
24 hours a day, seven days a week.
We have six power plant operators and
two power plant superintendents on staff.