And we’re in our central chilled plant,
which is attached to the heating plant.
We have our 3, 800 ton York
chillers in this plant,
and I’m just going to kinda go through …
The plant was put in in 2007 so this is coming
up on our 15th year of operation of this plant.
I’ll kinda walk you through some of the
piping that comes in and out of this chiller.
We’re gonna look at our flow
through the condenser first.
Up on the roof we have our cooling towers,
and we come out of the basin of the
cooling tower and go through a pump,
And that pumps the water down
through this pipe right here
and it comes in to the bottom
of the condenser on the chiller.
Now there’s a divider plate in this
green box on the end of the chiller
so the waters going through the
lower half of that condenser,
it makes a turn on the end of the condenser
and comes back through and then it comes
through this pipe over here and heads to the
top of the cooling tower that’s on the roof.
And once it gets there it
goes through a distribution
system that directs the water down through
nozzles and breaks the water up into
smaller droplets that drop down
through the fill in the tower,
and we have a fan that induces a draft
in that tower, where it sucks air in, and
that helps cool the water droplets off
and they fall into the basin on the bottom
of the cooling tower and collect
and the cycle starts over again.