We’re in the Mezz of the
chilled plant. Up on this level,
we have our three … condenser water pumps up here.
We have a bromine feeder which we feed bromine
into our cooling tower water to prevent Legionella
bacteria growing in the towers. Very important!
And we also have our switch gear up here. We
have our 4160v main disconnects for our chiller,
these three disconnects here.
And then over here we have
our motor starters, and our chiller
motors are a reduced voltage start.
Gives them a little chance to get going
without creating too much stress on them.
And over in this area, we
have our disconnects for our
pumps that are in the basement for our chilled
water, primary pumps, and then also our
oil freq drives on the chiller that vary the
oil pressure with the chiller compressor.