Right now, we’re in the Mezz of the chilled plant
and what we do on this level is we add chemical
to our tower water.
We have a chem meter right here that … senses
the amount of mineral that we have in the water
and then it operates a blow-down valve and
reduces that amount of mineral in the water.
We do that so we don’t foul our
condenser tubes on the chillers.
Our pumps here are 60 HP apiece on these pumps and
it takes the water out of the basin of the cooling
tower, comes down to the inlet of the pump,
and it increases the pressure of that water,
And that water goes down to the bottom pass of
the condenser and returns back and goes to the
top of the cooling tower where that water is
sent through the cooling tower to cool it off.
Generally, we kinda go … like to see the
water come back at like 75 deg, 70 deg,
and then we add about 10 deg to that
when it goes through the condenser.
For efficiency, the lower you bring
that temperature back the more
efficient that chiller will be. But
if you get a day that’s really hot,
and a lot of humidity, you don’t
get a very good heat transfer.
It's hard to remove heat and humidity in
the water with air that is really humid.
In those cases, we have to throttle
back our chillers at a reduced capacity.
And our power fans are
controlled with frequency drives
and those are right here. We have three
of those, one for each cooling tower.
Our pumps for the condensers they're
a solid, they’re a steady-flow pump.
We need that to provide a steady flow
of water through those condensers.