Right now we’re in our lower
level of our chilled plant.
This device right here is our air separator.
The return line from our secondary loop,
which feeds the buildings and
air handlers in those buildings,
comes back and any air that is entrained in the
water is separated out in this air separator.
Then what it does is it comes across
and we go into our primary chilled water pumps
which take off of this header and increase the
pressure on that water and force it to go
up through the evaporator on the chiller.
And then that water, after it goes through the
evaporator, returns back down and comes back
around and goes into a header for our secondary
loop pumps which pump the water around campus.
And that’s these three pumps on this side over
here, and they are 150 HP … motors on these pumps,
and its more redundant capacity there, we don’t
really need it. Generally, we run with just one
secondary loop pump at a time.
And, those are on variable frequency drives.
So, we control our flow that we have going out
in that secondary loop. We maintain a 10 PSI
differential between our supply and return lines.