We’re in the basement of our chilled plant
and what we’re looking at here is our supply
line right here going out that feeds the loop
around campus (the secondary chilled water loop).
And that goes to the air handlers
in the buildings around campus to provide the 45
deg water for the cooling coils in those areas.
And over here is our return
line that brings the 55 deg
water back to our chilled plant to be
cooled down again to 45 deg and sent out.
Right over here, the first piece of
equipment we go through is a air separator.
So, if we have any air in that chilled water
returning that’s where we take it out at.
We also add some water treatment into
the secondary chilled water loop just
to prevent corrosion on the inside
of our piping; to protect our piping.
And over here we have a sand filter. And
what that does is it will pick up any
small particulate, or small fine
pieces of rust, it filters it out.
And then when this backflushes it
will flush that down the drain.
This piece of equipment here, when it
backflushes, it goes through 600 gallons of water
per backflush cycle. And that
goes once a day, it backflushes.