We’re on the roof of the chilled plant, and
what we have behind me is the cooling towers,
starting on the north that’s #1, #2 in
the middle, and #3 on the south here.
Our water comes from the basin of the cooling
tower flows through the condenser water pumps
which were in the Mezz just down below here,
and the pressure is increased on that water.
It’s pumped down through the condenser and is
brought back up through the piping here, back
up to the top of the cooling tower where
it goes through some distributor nozzles.
That water’s broken up,
and it drops down through the
fill area, and we have a fan up
on top of this cooling tower that induces a draft.
And that draft cools that water down
about 10 deg before it returns to the sump
and is pumped around to the chiller again.