This is our cooling tower, or one of our
cooling towers, in the roof of the chill plant.
And what we’re looking at is our
inducer fan which induces a draft.
it’s a pretty fan with a lot of blades on it!
You can see the belt drive and
that’s on a frequency drive so
depending on how much cooling we need
that fan will speed up or slow down.
That’s all based off our water temp
leaving the basin and going to the chiller.
And the black material here
is what they call fill,
and the water droplets are
dropping down through that fill,
and then we’re bringing air from
outside the cooling tower with
this fan and pushing the exhaust air up
through the top of the cooling tower.
Yeah, normally we’d have water if we were
up and running, we’d have this filled,
and we’d have about 18 inches of water
in this sump when the chillers off.
When it’s running and the pumps running,
the water level drops about 4 inches and
that’s mostly water that’s falling down through
the fill, that's where it goes at that time.