Boilers rely on the combustion process of
fuel to provide the heat required to produce
steam inside the water-filled tubes.
The burner mixes the fuel and air together, and,
with the assistance of an ignition device
provides a platform for combustion.
This burner incorporates a blower that supplies
combustion air at a pressure high enough to
compensate for the airflow resistance inside
the boiler.
Three types of heat transfer mechanisms occur
during the combustion process inside the boiler:
radiation, convection, and conduction.
Each of these mechanisms transfers heat from the
burning fuel to the water in the boiler,
where the combustion air temperature can go up to 500 °F.
The university has used natural gas as the primary fuel
for all boilers to reduce campus pollution emissions.
Natural gas emits about 50% less carbon dioxide than
coal and 28% less carbon dioxide than fuel oil.
The emission of nitrogen oxides is nearly
five times less than burning coal
and three times less than burning fuel oil.