Here we are in the central control room where the
boiler operators monitor and control the boilers.
This state-of-the-art control
system has been implemented
since 2021 using PLC technology and
a system of cameras and sensors.
These interactive screens like the
one you see in Picture 1 are touch
screen Human-Machine-Interface (HMI) displays.
They give the boiler operator an overview of
the entire operation of the system in real time,
including states and measurements
of air, water, steam, and fuel.
They also make the control and operation
of devices around the plant such as valves,
sensors, pumps, and motors more accurate,
efficient, reliable, and user-friendly.
These direct interactions are made
through a computerized automatic
system called Supervisory Control and
Data Acquisition or SCADA for short.
The SCADA system consists of software and
hardware elements that allow the operators
to control steam-producing processes
locally or at a remote location;
monitor, gather, and process real-time
data, and record events into a log file.
The SCADA software processes, distributes,
and displays the data, helping operators and
facility management personnels analyze
the data and make important decisions.
Picture 1 gives you an overview of Boiler 2, which
is hundreds of feet away from this control room.
We can also see this same screen in front
of Boiler 2 on the main plant ground floor.
Here is our combustion chamber
with two burners running.
The boiler is making 19.4-kilo pounds of
steam per hour at a pressure of 98.3 PSIG.
The number 22.8 kSCFH along the yellow
pipe on this screen suggests that the
boiler uses 22.8 kilos standard cubic feet
of natural gas per hour for its burners.
Also, the silver pipe at the bottom
indicates that the boiler is taking
4,457 standard cubic feet of supply air at 60.4
degrees Fahrenheit for the combustion process.
Picture 2 here just tells us the steam
trends, how much steam flow the boilers make,
and what the water level inside the boiler
is on a real-time or hourly and daily basis.
There are two teams of three
staff staying here 24/7.
The boiler operator is responsible for the entire
shift and will report to the superintendent.
Together, they are in charge of the shift,
making all the decisions for all
operations in the heating plant.