Boilers rely on the combustion process of
fuel to provide the heat required to produce
steam inside the boiler.
Fuel contains some basic elements like carbon,
hydrogen, and sulfur.
Inside the boiler’s combustion chamber,
these elements react with oxygen and nitrogen
from the supplied air to
generate heat and form carbon dioxide, nitrogen
oxides, sulfur dioxides, and water vapor.
Two types of fuel sources are used at the
Central Heating Plant: natural gas and low-sulfur
diesel fuel oil.
Natural gas emits about 28% less carbon dioxide
and three times less nitrogen oxides than
fuel oil.
The Plant uses natural gas as the primary
fuel to reduce campus pollution emissions,
operations,
and maintenance costs.
Fuel oil is only used as a backup fuel source.
Fuel Valve Train.
In burner combustion systems, the gas valve
train, also known as the fuel valve train,
as seen in Figure 1, is the mechanical assembly
that introduces and interrupts fuel supply
to the burner.
The gas valve train helps ensure the boiler
operates safely by starting or stopping the
fuel flow into the
system.
It both monitors and regulates fuel pressure
within the system.
The gas valve train consists of multiple components
mounted on a steel rack, including pressure
regulating valves, fuel oil flow control and
metering devices, and safety shut-off valves. Combustion Efficiency.
The quantity of heat generated by the complete
combustion of a unit of a specific fuel is
constant and is termed the “heating value”
or “heat of combustion” of that fuel.
The efficiency of a boiler that involves the
combustion of a fuel is based on the heating
value of the fuel, which is the amount of
heat released when a unit amount of fuel at
room temperature is completely burned and
the combustion products are cooled to the
room temperature.
Then, the boiler performance can be characterized
by combustion efficiency as seen in the formulas
in Figure 2.
Most fuels contain hydrogen, which forms water
when burned, and the heating value of a fuel
will be different depending on whether the
water in combustion products is in liquid
or vapor form.
The heating value is called “lower heating
value”, or LHV, when the water in the combustion
gases is a vapor, and “higher heating value”,
or HHV, when the water in the combustion gases
is completely condensed, and thus the heat
of vaporization is also recovered.
The LHV is often used as the measure of energy
per kg of fuel supplied to the gas or gas
turbine engine because the exhaust gases have
such a high temperature that the water formed
is a vapor as it leaves the engine with other
combustion products.
The HHV is often used as the measure of energy
per kilogram of fuel supplied to the steam
power cycle because there are heat transfer
processes within the cycle that absorb enough
energy from the products of combustion that
some of the water vapor formed during combustion
will condense.