A thermodynamic cycle is a sequence of processes
that begins and ends at the same state.
A
system has completed a thermodynamic cycle
when the system undergoes a series of processes
and then returns to its original state, so
that the properties of the system at the end
of the cycle
are the same as at its beginning.
For example, refrigerant circulating through
a chiller executes
a cycle.
A vapor compression refrigeration cycle typically
has four processes.
Process 1 to 2 is the Isentropic compression
in a compressor.
Process 2 to 3 is the Constant-pressure
heat rejection in a condenser.
Process 3 to 4 is the throttling in an
expansive device.
Process 4 to 1 is the Constant-pressure
heat absorption in an evaporator
When a heat engine is run thermodynamically
backward, it becomes a heat
pump, a refrigerator, or an air conditioner,
depending on your point of view.
When a heat engine runs backward (or in reverse),
it receives a net input of work
W that causes an amount of heat QL to be removed
from a low-temperature
region and an amount of heat QH to be added
to a high-temperature region.
So, it
actually cools the low-temperature region
and heats the high-temperature region.
A backward-running heat engine is a refrigeration
machine, but its technical name
depends on exactly how it is being used.
For example, if food occupies the lowtemperature
region, then the device is indeed called a
refrigerator, but if people
occupy the low-temperature region, then the
device is called an air conditioner.
On the other hand, if people occupy the high-temperature
region and utilize QH
for space-heating purposes, then the device
is called a heat pump.
Though the
details of their design and operation differ
slightly, refrigerators, air conditioners,
and heat pumps can all be modeled as backward-running
heat engines.
The distinctions between a refrigerator and
a heat pump are shown in the next
figure.
A heat pump is a thermodynamic system operating
in a thermodynamic cycle that
removes heat from a low-temperature body and
delivers heat to a high
temperature body.
To accomplish this energy transfer, the heat
pump receives
external energy in the form of work or heat
from the surroundings.
While the name “heat pump” is the thermodynamic
term used to describe a cyclic
device that allows the transfer of heat energy
from a low temperature to a higher
temperature, we use the terms “refrigerator”
and “heat pump” to apply to
particular devices.
Here a refrigerator is a device that operates
on a thermodynamic
cycle and extracts heat from a low-temperature
medium.
The heat pump also
operates on a thermodynamic cycle but rejects
heat to the high-temperature
medium.
The efficiency of a refrigerator or heat pump
is expressed in terms of the
coefficient of performance, or COP.
For the refrigerator the desired result is
the heat supplied at the low temperature
and the input is the net work into the device
to make the cycle operate.
The
performance of refrigeration cycles can be
described as the ratio of the amount of
energy received by the system from the low-temperature
medium, QL, to the net
work into the system to accomplish this effect,
Wnet, in.
For the heat pump acting like a refrigerator
or an air conditioner, the primary
function of the device is the transfer of
heat from the low- temperature system.
The performance of heat pumps can be described
as the ratio of the amount of
energy discharged from the system to the high-temperature
medium, QH, to the
net work into the system to accomplish this
effect, Wnet, in.
For a reversible cycle, a reversed Carnot
cycle is called a Carnot refrigerator cycle.
The coefficients of performance of Carnot
refrigerators and heat pumps are
expressed in terms of temperatures as illustrated
in the diagram below.