Attached to the heating plant
is the central chiller plant
that has been operating since 2007,
consisting of three 800 Ton chillers.
These highly efficient, industrial-grade
units, provide chilled water to 20 buildings
on campus through over ten thousand
feet of insulated underground piping.
The chilled supply water enters the
building and flows through a heat
exchanger, absorbing heat from the building space
before recirculating back to the central
plant through a closed-loop return line.
The central heating and chiller plants at UW Stout
constitute an efficient way of air conditioning
and heating the high-density building clusters
on the campus called District Energy Systems.
By delivering thermal energy directly in a usable
form and combining loads for multiple buildings,
District Energy Systems create economies of scale
that drive efficiency and reduce energy costs.
According to the United Nations Environment
Program, known as UNEP, District Energy
Systems represent a best practice approach
that can help cities, populated urban areas,
and campuses “to move towards climate-resilient,
resource-efficient, and low-carbon pathways.”
Many equipment, processes, and systems in the
heating and chiller plants are relevant resources
for students in environmental science, applied
science, engineering, and engineering technology.