A heat exchanger typically involves two flowing
fluids separated by a solid wall of a metal tube.
For the condenser, the first fluid is hot
refrigerant entering the condenser shell from the
compressor, and the second fluid is the condenser
water entering the tube from the cooling tower.
The pumps causing the condenser
water to flow across the
tubes are located outside the chiller
on the second floor of this plant.
To control the growth of slime,
which is organic bacteria and algae,
that can significantly reduce the efficiency
of cooling by reducing heat transfer,
oxidizing biocide like bromine
are fed in the condenser water.
For the evaporator, the first fluid
is cold liquid refrigerant entering
the evaporator shell from the
expansion valve and the second
fluid is the return chilled water
entering the tube from the buildings.
The pumps causing the chilled water to flow across
the tubes are on the basement floor of this plant.
Heat is first transferred from the hot
fluid to the tube wall by convection,
through the wall by conduction, and from the
wall to the cold fluid again by convection.
Any radiation effects are usually included
in the convection heat transfer coefficients.
Heat exchangers are normally
well-insulated devices that
allow energy exchange between hot and
cold fluids without mixing the fluids.