All chillers at the Central Cooling
Plant are YORK MaxE chillers, Model YK.
Each chiller produces a cooling capacity
of 800 tons using refrigerant R134a.
The chiller consists of an open
motor mounted to a compressor,
condenser, evaporator, and variable
flow control or expansion valve.
The chiller is controlled by the Microcomputer
Control Center that monitors its operation. The
operating status, temperatures, pressures, and
other information pertinent to operation of the
chiller are automatically displayed
and read on the graphic display.
Let’s look at the water-cooled chiller
and its diagram in the inserted pictures:
In operation, water at 54 degrees Fahrenheit from
the primary circuit flows through the evaporator,
where boiling refrigerant absorbs heat, making
it become chilled water at 44 degrees Fahrenheit.
The chilled water is then piped through a
secondary circuit to buildings around campus.
From here, it flows through fan coil
units or other air conditioning units,
absorbing heat from the air at
terminal buildings. The warmed
water is then returned to the chiller
to complete the chilled water circuit.
The refrigerant vapor, which is produced
by the boiling action in the evaporator,
flows to the compressor where a
rotating impeller increases its
pressure and temperature, then
discharges into the condenser.
Condenser water at about 85 degrees Fahrenheit
flows through the condenser tubes absorbing heat
from the hot refrigerant vapor. This causes
the refrigerant to condense. After the heat
absorption process, the condenser water becomes
warmer, at around 95 degrees Fahrenheit. It is
then pumped into a cooling tower where it yields
the most heat energy to the fast-moving air inside
the tower. Afterward, the water flows back to the
condenser to complete the condenser water circuit.
Meanwhile, the condensed refrigerant drains
from the condenser into the liquid return line,
where a variable orifice meters the flow of liquid
refrigerant to the evaporator. This
completes the refrigerant circuit.