Water treatment is required to maintain
peak performance, reduce water consumption,
and minimize corrosion, scale, and fouling
while controlling microbial growth.
Water quality is controlled by
a combination of pretreatment
for makeup water and chemical treatment.
Pretreatment for makeup water, sometimes
called mechanical filtration, is used to
remove suspended particles. Pretreatment for
makeup water consists of the following elements:
Water softeners (for removal of
calcium and magnesium hardness)
Reverse osmosis (which can remove up to 99% of
minerals and dissolved solids from
the water leaving almost pure H2O).
Reverse osmosis is a process in which reactive,
colloidal silica, and dissolved salts can be
removed from water by forcing the water through
a semi-permeable membrane under high pressure.
Contaminants that are not removed mechanically by
pretreatment equipment must be treated chemically.
Once in the feedwater, dissolved gases, hardness,
and dissolved minerals must be treated
to prevent deposition and corrosion.