Chemical treatment is used to control
corrosion, scaling, biofouling,
and biothreats. Minerals can cause a buildup of
deposits and cause overheating of boiler parts.
Corrosion weakens boiler metal by
the thinning (removal) of the metal.
Corrosion causes pitting and channeling of the
metal, which results in the thinning of tubes,
piping, and other boiler components. Corrosion is
primarily caused by oxygen in the boiler water.
Feedwater is treated to remove oxygen
by heating and/or chemical treatment.
De-aerators are used for removal of
dissolved gases, especially oxygen and CO2.
Heating the feedwater removes oxygen
and carbon dioxide. Chemical treatment
requires the addition of oxygen-scavenger
chemicals. An oxygen scavenger chemical
is a chemical that combines with oxygen to form
harmless compounds for removal from the boiler.
Sodium sulfite is an oxygen scavenger that
is commonly used to treat boiler water.
Sodium sulfite combines with oxygen to form sodium
sulfate, which accumulates at the bottom of the
boiler. The sodium sulfate is then discharged
from the boiler through the bottom blowdown valve.