Feedwater used in the boiler should be free from
any dissolved gases and oxygen. The deaerator is
used for this. The main purpose of a deaerator is
to deaerate gas, a process called degasification,
from the feedwater. Also, it serves as a
storage tank where feedwater is pumped into
the boiler. It is the place where feedwater
is preheated before entering the boiler.
To preheat the feedwater, low-pressure
steam is utilized. Low-pressure steam is
also used to remove dissolved oxygen from water.
The heating plant is currently using spray and
tray-type deaerators to remove
dissolved gases in feedwater.
In this type of deaerator, water enters from
the top. Water is distributed through a set of
nozzles, as shown in the next figure.
Water falls into the bottom storage
tank from the deaerator column through
the perforated tray and small droplets
are formed. Low pressure steam is
supplied to the steam distributor.
This steam moves up into the deaerator column and
comes in contact with droplets of the feedwater.
Feedwater is heated up to the boiling point
corresponding to the deaerator pressure.
Due to the formation of small water
droplets, the contact surface exposed
to steam increases which results in
complete removal of the dissolved gases.
By heating the water, dissolving
capacity of gases in the water decreases.
So, dissolved gases are removed from the water
easily. These removed gases along with some
non-condensing vapour present in the steam,
is vented to the atmosphere through a vent.
The vent is fitted with an orifice and
a bypass valve. The deaerated water is
then collected in a tank called a storage tank.
If there is still dissolved gas which
is not removed at the deaerator column,
then it is removed here due to large
surface area of the heated water.
Initially, when feedwater
is at a normal temperature,
heating steam is used to heat the water.