Here is the top of boiler number
1 where the combustion product,
or flue gases inside the boiler, are
going to be released to the chimney.
Flue gases are generally in the temperature
range of 400 to 500 degrees Fahrenheit,
so there is a huge amount of losses from the
boiler if we cannot utilize this heat energy.
The university has installed a heat recovery
device called the economizer to recover some
of the heat from the flue gases for
heating the feed water into the boiler.
An economizer is a heat exchanger device that
preheats feed water before
it gets fed to the boiler.
Since the heat energy is given to the
water, the requirement of fuel for
producing steam is optimized. Because of
that, we call this device an economizer.
The Economizer works on the principle of heat
transfer that usually takes place from high
temperature to low temperature. As shown in the
figure of a heat exchanger, hot flue gas enters
on the shell side and water the on tube side with
an extended heating surface like Fins or Gills.
Flue gases from the boiler outlet are at
high a temperature and feed water that
needs to be preheated is at a low temperature.
So, this temperature difference between
the water and flue gases helps to increase
the feed water temperature and reduce the
heat load on the boiler to a great extent.
The economizer reduces not only consumption but
also the overall energy costs, environmental
impact, and carbon footprint. The economizer can
boost system efficiency by 3% to 5% on average.