The underground piping network system
distributes steam and chilled water
generated from the Plant to buildings
around the campus to serve their heating
and cooling needs. Underground
systems are used because of their
aesthetics and safety
issues. They are closed-loop systems.
That means that steam is generated at the
Plant, sent via underground pipes to the
buildings to be used, then the steam is
condensed back to water which is then pumped
back to the Plant to be reused. This
network also includes the underground
piping system that collects warmed water
after chilled water has been used at the
buildings. The steam piping system is about
5 miles in length and serves 51 buildings
across campus, while the chilled water
piping system is about two miles long
and serves 20 buildings, mainly on South
Campus. Several buildings contain old steam
and condensate pipes installed in 1916 and still
have insulation with asbestos, which are buried
underground. Significant parts of
the steam and condensate system are
pre-insulated cast iron pipes running in
concrete surface trenches or deep-buried
small tunnels. Steam pipe sizes vary from
2.5 to 10 inches and condensate pipes
employ smaller sizes ranging from 1.5 to 5
inches. Heat transfer in buried systems is
influenced by the thermal conductivity of
the soil and by the depth of burial,
particularly when the system's thermal
insulation has a low thermal resistance.
All directly buried underground chilled
water piping systems use 4-inch to 18-inch
diameter HDPE pipes and can handle
working pressure up to 350 PSIG.