Boilers rely on the combustion process of fuel to
provide the heat required to produce steam inside
the boiler. A burner is a group of devices that
introduce fuel and air into a furnace, mix them
together, and provide a platform for combustion
with the assistance of an ignition device.
The burner incorporates a blower
that supplies combustion air at
a pressure high enough to compensate for
the airflow resistance inside the boiler.
Like all burners in the plant,
this burner uses natural gas as
the primary fuel and fuel oil
as an auxiliary support fuel.
Atomization breaks liquid fuel oil into
fine particles when admitted into the
furnace. Atomization is done mechanically
by blowing air or steam into the burner.
Fuel contains some basic elements like carbon,
hydrogen, and sulfur. Inside the combustion
chamber, these elements react with oxygen and
nitrogen from the supplied air to liberate
heat and form carbon dioxide, nitrogen
oxides, sulfur dioxides, and water vapor.
The university has used natural gas as its
primary fuel for all boilers to reduce campus
pollution emissions. Natural gas emits
about 50% less carbon dioxide than coal
and 28% less carbon dioxide than fuel
oil. The emission of nitrogen oxides
is nearly five times less than burning coal
and three times less than burning fuel oil.
Three types of heat transfer mechanisms occur
during the combustion process inside the boiler:
radiation, convection, and conduction.
Each of these mechanisms transfers heat
from the burning fuel to the water in the boiler,
where the combustion air temperature
can go up to 500 degrees Fahrenheit.