Boiler 2 and Boiler 3 in the next row are D-type
water-tube boilers produced by Wickes Boiler
in the 1960s as coal-fired boilers and have
been producing steam at the plant since 1965.
By March 4, 2020, the university made
the switch to natural gas as the main
fuel for all boilers at the plant to
reduce campus emissions, operations,
and maintenance
costs.
According to the United States
Energy Information Administration,
burning natural gas emits about half of the
carbon dioxide, or CO2, as burning coal.
Using natural gas also helps eliminate equipment
and labor cost for coal and ash handling controls.
Now, all boilers can use fuel
oil as a backup fuel source.
The tubes extend between an upper header, called
a steam drum, and a lower header, called a water
drum or sometimes, a mud drum. Tubes are either
straight or bent into simple or complex shapes.
Water-tube boilers are designed to circulate hot
combustion gases or flue gas around the outside
of a large number of water-filled tubes.
As the flue gas passes through the tubes,
it heats the tubes, which then heats the water.
As more heat is transferred, the water
temperature keeps rising until it
reaches the saturation temperature, and water
changes phase from liquid to vapor or steam.
The temperature of saturated steam
rises when pressure is increased,
and the temperature goes down
when the pressure is decreased.
For example, the temperature of
saturated steam is 212 degrees
Fahrenheit at the atmospheric pressure
of zero pounds per square inch (or PSI).
However, inside the boiler where
the pressure is set at 100 PSI,
the temperature of saturated steam
increases to 338 degrees Fahrenheit.
A plot showing this relationship is known in
Thermodynamics as liquid-vapor saturation curve.
Boiler 2 can produce 25,000 pounds of
steam per hour at the pressure of 100 PSI,
and temperature of 338 degrees Fahrenheit.
This steam is sent out to the buildings on
campus through underground piping systems.