The boiler is considered the heart
of a central heating system where
it generates high-pressure steam and
sends it to buildings around campus.
Boiler 4 is an O-type water-tube boiler
produced by Cleaver-Brooks and was put
into operation in 1973. It can generate
about 90,000 pounds of saturated steam
per hour at a pressure of 114.7 PSI and
a temperature of 338 degrees Fahrenheit.
This section will explain how steam
is generated inside the boiler.
Water-tube boilers are designed to
circulate hot combustion gases from the
burner around the outside of a
large number of water-filled tubes.
As the flue gas passes through the tubes, it heats
the tubes, which then heats the water. When water
is heated in the boiler at atmospheric pressure,
the water temperature increases until the boiling
point or saturated temperature, and the volume of
water increases slightly. Once the water reaches
saturation temperature (the temperature
at which it will boil at that pressure),
the water temperature remains there even
if heat is added. The heat added does
not increase the water temperature, but the
water gets converted from liquid into steam.
Bubbles of steam are produced and
rise to the steam drum on the top
of the boiler. These bubbles
burst and release steam into
the space above the steam drum and
are ready to enter the steam system.
The saturated temperature of steam varies
with the boiler pressure at which water is
heated. The saturated temperature
rises when pressure is increased,
and the temperature goes down
when pressure is decreased.
For example, the saturated temperature of the
steam is 212 degrees Fahrenheit at the atmospheric
pressure of 14.7 psi. This state of steam is
represented by point A on a diagram called the
Liquid-vapor saturation curve of water. Inside the
boiler, where the pressure is set at 114.7 psi,
the temperature of saturated steam increases
to 338 degrees Fahrenheit at point B.