Attached to the heating plant
is the central chiller plant
that has been operating since 2007,
consisting of three 800 Ton chillers.
These highly efficient, industrial-grade
units produce a chilled water for supply
to 16 buildings on the campus through
an insulated underground piping network.
The chilled supply water enters the
building and flows through a heat
exchanger, absorbing heat from the building space
before recirculating back to the central
plant through a closed-loop return line.
The central heating and chiller plants at UW Stout
constitute an efficient way of air conditioning
and heating the high-density building clusters
on campus called "District Energy Systems."
By delivering thermal energy directly in a useable
form and combining loads for multiple buildings,
District Energy Systems create economies of scale
that drive efficiency and reduce energy costs.
According to the United Nations Environment
Program, usually known as UNEP for short,
District Energy Systems represent a
best-practice approach that can help
cities, populated urban areas, and campuses
to move forward towards climate-resilient,
resource-efficient, and low-carbon pathways.
The equipment, processes, and systems
in the heating and chiller plants
are relevant resources for students in
environmental science, applied science,
engineering, and engineering technology.