UW Stout Library’s Mechanical Room.
We are in a mechanical room on the
sixth floor of UW Stout’s library.
The key equipment in the room is the
air handling unit, commonly called AHU.
The AHU is responsible for heating and
cooling the five-story library that
provides seating capacity for 1,086 readers
and space for 400,000 volumes of work.
Three AHUs in this mechanical room
can provide conditioned air to 123,000
square feet of the library at up
to 75000 cubic feet per minute.
An AHU is a mechanical device used to regulate and
circulate air as part of a heating, ventilating,
and air-conditioning (HVAC) system.
It is usually a large metal box containing
a blower, heating and cooling coils, filter
racks, a mixing chamber, and dampers.
Air handlers usually connect to a
ductwork ventilation system that
distributes the conditioned air through
the building and returns it to the AHU.
The operation of an AHU is illustrated
in a schematic in Figure 1.
You can relate this schematic to the key parts of
an actual AHU in this mechanical room in Figure 2.
Let’s start with the cold outside
air on the left of the schematic.
Air handling units collect air from outside, which
is treated and distributed throughout the rooms.
They also recycle part of the returned
air from indoors and mix it with the
outside air in the mixing chamber to save energy.
Mixed air then flows through filters.
Depending on the air purity requirements,
the filter applied will have a higher or
lower particle, virus, bacteria, odor, and
other air pollutants retention levels.
During the COVID-19 pandemic, filters
in an HVAC's air handling unit are a
first line of defense in removing
virus germs from recirculated air.
The conservation principle
applied to the mixing chamber is
illustrated in Figure 3.
After filtration, air flows through heating
and cooling coils where it is either heated
up or cooled down to meet the required indoor
temperature for both comfort and efficiency.
Heating and cooling coils are heat exchangers that
transfer temperature between steam and air in the
case of the heating coil and between chilled
water and air in the case of the cooling coil.
The humidifier and dehumidifier are optional parts
of an AHU if humidity control
of the indoor air is desired.
The conservation principle applied to the heating
and cooling coils is illustrated in Figure 4.
The supply fan is on the
far right of the schematic.
It is an electromechanical system that
powers the air to expel it from the
AHU to the ducts that distribute
the air throughout the library.