Here we are on the mezzanine of the
heating plant and these two big green tanks
are deaerators. A deaerator is a device
that is widely used for the removal of air
and other dissolved gases from the
feedwater to steam generating boilers.
Specifically, dissolved oxygen in boiler
feed waters will cause serious corrosion
damage in steam systems by attaching
to the walls of metal piping and other
metallic equipment and forming oxides
or rust. It also combines with any
dissolved carbon dioxide to form carbonic
acid, which causes further corrosion.
Figure 2 is a schematic diagram of a
tray-type deaerator. It has a vertical domed
deaeration section mounted above a
horizontal boiler feedwater storage vessel.
Boiler feedwater enters the vertical
dearation section above the perforated trays
and flows downward through the
perforations. Low-pressure dearation steam
enters below the perforated trays and
flows upward through the perforations.
The perforated trays provide good contact
and mixing between the steam and the
boiler feed water. The steam strips
dissolved gas from the boiler feedwater and
exits via the vent at the top of the
domed section. The deaerated water flows
down into the horizontal storage vessel
from which it is pumped to the steam
generating boiler system. External insulation
of the vessel is typically provided to
minimize heat loss.
Deaerators provide many benefits
to the boiler system, including:
Serving as a surge collection tank
for process condensate return.
Blending hot return condensate
and cold makeup water.
Preheating feedwater uniformly
to improve boiler efficiency, and
Removing oxygen (O2) and carbon dioxide
(CO2) from feedwater to mitigate
corrosion.
Most deaerators are American Society of
Mechanical Engineers- (ASME-) certified
pressure vessels that operate at 5 to
15 psig and at a water temperature of
225°Fahrenheit, which is the minimum
temperature required to remove dissolved
O2 and CO2 from feedwater. A deaerator
is not only an essential auxiliary
component of a reliable feedwater system,
but the heart of a boiler mass-flow
and thermal-energy database that can be
used to critique plant operations and
identify energy-savings opportunities.