We are standing in front of Combustion
Air Fan 3 on the basement floor.
A fan is an air pump: a machine that creates
a pressure difference and causes airflow.
The impeller imparts to the
air static and kinetic energy,
which varies in proportion,
depending on the type of fan.
Fans are classified as centrifugal or axial flow
fans according to the direction
of airflow through the impeller.
The general configuration of a
centrifugal fan is shown in Figure 1.
A typical application of centrifugal fans at UW
Stout’s central heating plant involves combustion
air blowers that provide air at the right
temperature and pressure to the boilers’ burners.
A general configuration of an axial
flow fan is shown in Figure 2.
A typical application of axial fans at
UW Stout’s central chiller plant involves
electric fans within cooling towers that
create airflows and remove heat from warm
condenser
water.
Except for Boiler 1, which has its
combustion air blower attached to
the unit on the main floor, three
other boilers have their combustion
air blowers located on the
basement floor of the plant.
Figure 3 illustrates Fan 3’s Station supplying
combustion air to Boiler 3 above.
Fan 3 is a centrifugal fan driven by an electric
motor.
The motor’s speed and torque are controlled
by an electronic device called a
Variable Frequency Drive or VFD.
The VFD controls the fan's output depending
on the amount of air demanded by the boiler.
Fan 3 also has an Inlet Vane Damper
to control the low flow at a very
low load during the start and closing burner.
A fan damper is similar to air vents in your car.
You can open or close louvers
to adjust the airflow;
Increase by opening the damper
and decrease by closing it.
The fan and motor speeds remain constant.
The Inlet Vane Damper is installed
on the fan's inlet and swirls the
inlet air in the same direction as the
fan rotation to alter fan performance.
They are commonly modulated with
electric or pneumatic actuators.
Working together with VFD, the
Inlet Vane Damper can help Fan
3 be more responsive on load reduction control.
The centrifugal fan often generates
noise from the inlet during operation.
This noise is loud and considered an
occupational hazard because loud noise
can create physical and psychological
stress, reduce productivity, interfere
with communication and concentration,
and contribute to workplace accidents.
A silencer duct was installed to
reduce noise at the fan inlet.
In Thermodynamics, fans are considered
shaft work machines whose primary
function is to promote a work input
or output through a rotating shaft.
Shaft work machines are steady-state,
single-inlet single-outlet open systems.
The work produced or absorbed
by fans can then be determined
from the energy rate balance
equation, as seen in Figure 4.