A steam turbine is a mechanical device
that converts mechanical energy stored in
high-pressure flowing steam into
rotational mechanical energy. Turbines are
commonly used in power plants to produce
mechanical power that may be used
by a generator to produce electrical
power. At Stout’s heating plant, the
mechanical energy from the turbine is
used to run the feedwater pump, as seen
in Figure 1. The steam turbine drives this
feed pump to supply water to the boiler
units as needed. The feed pump raises
the feedwater to a pressure high enough
to enter the boiler. Steam turbine-driven feed
pumps are typical with high pressure water-tube
boiler installations. The turbine is supplied with
steam directly from the boiler and exhausts into a
back-pressure line which can be used
for feed heating.
A schematic of this steam turbine is shown
in Figure 2. It consists of two sets of
blades. The first set of blades, called
stationary blades, are fixed on a casing., The
second set of blades, called rotor blades,
are fixed on the rotor.. The steam is
directed by the stationary blades so
that it impinges on the rotating turbine
blades. During this process, momentum
is transferred from the fluid, causing a
torque on the rotating shaft. Stationary
blades are used to redirect the steam
between each set of rotating blades.
Steam enters the turbine at high pressure
and temperature. The pressure of steam
decreases as it flows from the inlet to
the outlet of the turbine. The specific
enthalpy of the steam also decreases as it
flows through the device since energy is
transferred from the fluid to the rotating
shaft. Figure 3 illustrates the typical
symbol used to represent the turbine
component in a cycle schematic.