Compressors and fans are essentially the
same devices. However, compressors are
capable of compressing gas at very high pressures.
Compressed air at the heating plant finds
application in operating pneumatic instruments
connected with boilers, fans, valves,
actuators, motors, and control systems.
The air system in the Plant is divided
into instrument air and service air.
As the name suggests, instrument
air is used to operate pneumatic
instruments where the quality of
the air is extremely important.
All control valves, pneumatic dampers, gates,
guide vanes, and solenoid valves operate using
instrument air, which is dry compressed air.
Figure 1 is the compressor system.
It can produce instrument air at
a rate of up to 125 cubic feet per
minute and at the pressure range of 90 to 110 psi.
Service air is required for
cleaning and purging of filters,
and it is compressed air directly
coming out of the compressor (Figure 2).
Its quality requirements are not as stringent
as those of instrument air, therefore,
there is no need to have air
dryer for service air.
Compressors, as well as pumps and fans, are
devices to increase the pressure of a fluid.
Work is supplied to these devices from an
external source through a rotating shaft.
Therefore, compressors involve work inputs.
If we neglect the changes in kinetic
and potential energies the steady-state,
steady-flow first law of the conservation of
energy equation will look like this in Figure 3.