Water pumps move chilled, condenser water
and feedwater to and from the refrigeration
equipment and associated ancillary equipment.
Pumps can be classified
into three broad categories:
(1) reciprocating, (2)
rotary, and (3) centrifugal.
Both reciprocating and rotary pumps
are positive displacement pumps.
They discharge a fixed amount of liquid
at a given speed.
The primary moving element
of a reciprocating pump is a
piston or plunger, while a rotary pump is a rotor.
The most frequently used pump in the heating,
ventilating, and air-conditioning industry is
a centrifugal pump with an enclosed impeller
and a volute casing, as seen in Figure 1.
In a centrifugal pump, an electric
motor or other power source rotates
the impellers at the motor’s rated speed.
Impeller rotation adds energy to
the fluid after it is directed
into the center of the rotating impeller.
Centrifugal pumps provide the primary
force to distribute and recirculate hot
and chilled water in various space
conditioning and plumping systems.
The pump provides predetermined water flow to the
space load terminal units or to a thermal
storage chamber for release at peak load.
At the central heating and chiller plant,
the hydronic systems that use pumps include:
Condensing water circuits to the cooling tower.
Chilled water pumps.
Boiler feeds.
Condensate returns as seen in Figures 2 and 3.
A boiler feed pump is a critical equipment used in
a boiler house that supplies deaerated
and LP-dosed feedwater to the boiler.
This pump must pump feedwater into
the boiler drum against the pressure.
So, discharged pressure of this pump is
higher than the boiler drum pressure.
A feed pump is a multistage pump driven
by an electrical motor or turbine.
Boiler feed and condensate return
pumps for steam boilers should be
selected based on the boiler
manufacturer’s requirements.
Centrifugal pumps can also be found in water
treatment and service water heating systems.
Pumps, as well as compressors and fans, are
devices that increase the pressure of a fluid.
Work is supplied to these devices from an
external source through a rotating shaft.
Therefore, pumps involve work inputs. If we
neglect the changes in kinetic and potential
energies as fluid flows through a pump having
one entrance and one exit, the steady-state,
steady-flow, the first law, or the conservation of
energy equation is presented in Figure 4.
As there is very little temperature
change across such hydraulic pumps,
the shaft work absorbed by pumps does not
depend on the temperature difference
between output and input fluids.