Cooling towers are large evaporative cooling
systems that can be used to reject heat from
a warm condenser water to the atmosphere
by a combination of heat and mass transfer.
Cooling towers can operate by natural or forced
convection. Also, they may be counter-flow,
cross-flow, or a combination of these.
Figure 1 is a cutaway picture
of a forced convection,
cross-flow cooling tower and Figure
2 shows its working principle.
The cooling tower contains a large fan
which blows air through the unit. The
warm condenser water about to be cooled enters
at 1 and is sprayed from the top of the tower.
The falling water usually passes
through the fill media intended
to keep it broken up into fine
drops to promote evaporation.
Atmospheric air drawn in at
3 by the fan flows upward,
counter to the direction of the falling
water droplets. As the two streams interact,
a fraction of the entering liquid water
stream evaporates into the moist air,
which exits at 4 with a greater humidity
ratio than the incoming moist air at 3,
while liquid water exits at 2 with a lower
temperature than the water entering at 1.
Since some of the incoming water is
evaporated into the moist air stream,
an equivalent amount of makeup water
is added at 5 so that the return mass
flow rate of the cool water equals the mass
flow rate of the warm water entering at 1.
For operation at a steady state, mass balances
for the dry air, and water and an energy balance
on the overall cooling tower, provide information
about the cooling tower performance. In applying
the energy balance, heat transfer with
the surroundings is usually neglected.
The power input to the fan of forced-convection
towers also may be negligible relative to other
energy rates involved. The example that follows
illustrates the analysis of a cooling tower
using conservation of mass and energy together
with property data for the dry air and water.
Each cooling tower can typically cool
2,400 gallons (about 9,084.98 L) per
minute of water from 95°F to 85°F at
72°F ambient wet bulb temperature.